Guide to the B. Traven Collection, 1917-1989
Department of Special Collections
B. Traven Collection,
1917-1989
Special Collections M0570
Klein, H. Arthur, collector.
6 linear feet.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of the estate of H. Arthur Klein, 1991.
Biographical Note
Herbert Arthur Klein, a journalist and author, and his wife, Mina Cooper Klein, had a life-long fascination with the works of B. Traven. For over fifty years, the Kleins collected many different kinds of material on Traven. They also translated and edited a collection of short stories by Traven, The Kidnapped Saint (Lawrence Hill, 1974).
Herbert Klein was born around 1907 in New York City. He received his A.B. from Stanford University and his M.A. from Occidental College. In addition, Klein pursued graduate studies at Columbia University, UCLA, Berkeley, and the Berlin Handelshochschule.
Klein began his career as a newspaperman, moving in 1930 to the Berlin office of the Chicago Tribune. Shortly thereafter he married. A couple of years later, he taught English at the Marxistische Arbeiter Schule in Berlin. Here one of his students first introduced him to the work of B. Traven, who was an especially popular author among German workers. The Kleins left Germany in 1933.
After returning to the U.S., Klein corresponded with Traven from 1933 to 1935 (about a dozen letters altogether). Mina Klein also wrote Traven a few times and was answered by a Señor Martinez, whom she strongly suspected was Traven. Although the Kleins never met Traven, after his death they did visit his widow, Rosa Elena Luján.
The Kleins lived most of their lives in Malibu, California, where the air was better for Herbert Klein's health. Mina Klein died in 1979, and Herbert Klein died about ten years later.
Klein's professional name was H. Arthur Klein. He and his wife wrote, edited, or translated over twenty books. Some of these were popular science and art books, such as The World of Measurements (1974), Peter Bruegel the Elder, Artist of Abundance (1968), and Käthe Kollwitz; Life in Art (1972). The Kleins also translated works by Wilhelm Busch from German into English. Although this collection contains several plans for a study of Traven, only The Kidnapped Saint was ever completed.
Scope and Content
This collection includes over fifty years' worth of materials on the author B. Traven collected by Herbert and Mina Klein. The holdings are divided into the following sections, which largely correspond to Herbert Klein's original ordering of the material.
Access Terms
Ballio, Tino.; Bang, Herman, 1857-1912.; Baumann, Friedel.; Baumann, Michael L.; Cheuse, Alan.; Gray, Robert.; Hagemann, E.R.( Edward R.), 1921-; Huston, John.; Johnson, William Weber, 1909-; Klein, Mina C.; Kohner, Paul.; Küpfer, Peter.; López Mateos, Esperanza.; Lujan, Rosa Elena.; Mermet, Irene.; Olafson, Robert.; Raskin, Jonah, 1942-; Recknagel, Rolf.; Spota, Luis.; Stevenson, Philip; Stone, Judy.; Traven, B.; Wieder, Josef.; Wyatt, Will.; Büchergilde Gutenberg.; Lawrence Hill & Co.; American literature--20th century.; Photoprints.; Phonotapes.; The B. Traven Newsletter.; Der Bücherfreund.; The Great Traven Hunt or Erica's Dream.; The Kidnapped Saint.; Rosa Blanca.; Stories by the Man Nobody Knows.
Series Description
- Series I. Correspondence
  This is arranged chronologically within each subsection: correspondence with B. Traven; with Traven's widow and publishers; and with Traven scholars, libraries, Klein's attorney, newspapers.
- Series II. Klein's manuscripts and notes for projects
- Series III. Subject Files
  This section has material on Traven arranged first by year (pre-1920-1985) and then alphabetically by subject.
- Series IV. Photos and audio tapes
- Series V. Books and play
  This section includes a paperback by Traven, a dissertation on Traven, and a play about Traven.
- Series VI. Serials
  Most of these periodicals have at least one article on Traven.
- Series VII. Addendum
  This is a list of serials dispersed throughout the collection.
Although Herbert and Mina Klein worked together closely on many of the projects described in the collection, almost all of the correspondence and notes are by Herbert Klein, who also seems to have assembled the original files. For simplicity's sake, Herbert Klein is referred to as Klein throughout the collection's description, while his wife is referred to by her full name. Some common abbreviations found throughout the material are BT for B. Traven, HAK for Herbert Arthur Klein, and MCK for Mina Cooper Klein.
Many of Herbert Arthur Klein's original folder titles were kept in this collection. What Klein labeled as original, especially in his correspondence with B. Traven, was often the carbon copy of his original letter. Moreover Klein often retyped the letters he received from Traven. A few true originals are included here in the Traven-Klein correspondence; where the original is in poor condition, a photocopy follows.
Prominent persons and institutions mentioned in this collection include:
Ballio, Tino
Baumann, Friedel
Baumann, Michael L.
Büchergilde Gutenberg
Hagemann, E.R.
Johnson, William
Klein, Herbert Arthur
Klein, Mina Cooper
Lawrence Hill & Co.
Kohner, Paul
Küpfer, Peter
López Mateos, Esperanza
Luján, Rosa Elena
Marut, Ret
Mermet, Irene
Olafson, Robert
Raskin, Jonah
Recknagel, Rolf
Rosa Blanca (film)
Spota, Luis
Stevenson, Phil
Stone, Judy
Traven, B.
Wieder, Josef
Wyatt, Will
Container List
- I. Correspondence (arranged chronologically within subsection)
  - With B. Traven
    - General index of Klein's letters to and from Traven (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Traven-Klein letters, 1933originals (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Traven-Klein letters, 1934originals (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Original Klein letter to Traven, 5/28/35 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Original Klein letter to Traven, 7/2/35 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Originals of material sent by Traven, 7/16/35 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Klein letter to Traven, 8/1/35 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Original Klein letter to Traven, 10/1/35 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Traven-Klein letters, 1933-35 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - With Traven's widow and publishers
    - Rosa Elena Lujan (Traven's widow), 1967-78 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, British publishers, 1936-59 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lawrence Hill & Co., Hill & Wang, Inc., 1966-70 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lawrence Hill & Co., 1971-73 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lawrence Hill & Co., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lawrence Hill & Co., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lawrence Hill & Co., 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Contracts and royalty reports from L. Hill, 1975-79 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Penn State Press, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Allison and Busby, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ken Saunders, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - With Traven scholars, libraries, Klein's attorney, newspapers
    - E.R. Hagemann, 1959-60 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Phil Stevenson, 1961-73(also has letters from Traven to Stevenson) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Grad student, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Judy Stone, 1975(also notes on her book) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jonah Raskin, 1975-79 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Rectification letters, UCLA Special Collections, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - William Weber Johnson, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Paul Kohner, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - George Hanson, 1976-78 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Michael Baumann, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Tino Ballio, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Ernst Schürer, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Traven Conference correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Rolf Recknagel, 1976-[82?] (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Karl Guthke, 1982-3 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Peter Küpfer, 1982-3 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Martha Müller, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Klein's attorney Lauri Provencher, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - NY Review of Books, June 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - LA Times, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series II. Klein's manuscripts and notes for projects
  - Kleins' work on Traven stories
    - Editing notecards for Traven tales (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Special materials on Jungle or Mahogany novels (book jackets, correspondence with publishers, translations that later appeared in Kleins' book) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Master file, The Kidnapped Saint (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - (Primarily first drafts of translations for The Kidnapped Saint)
    - The Kidnapped Saint (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Submission (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Story of a Bomb (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Diplomat (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Frustration (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Reviving the Dead (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Accomplices (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Indian Dance in the Jungle (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Introduction, In the Freest State in the World (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - In the Freest State in the World (text) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - In the Freest State in the World (endnotes) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Rejected stories: Burro Trading #6 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Rejected stories: Unexpected Solution #12 [original missing] (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Rejected stories: Welfare Hospital #13 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Rejected stories: Foreign Correspondent #14 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Rejected stories: Dynamite #15 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Rejected stories: The Guard #16 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Primarily second drafts of translations for The Kidnapped Saint
    - Submission #2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Diplomats #3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - In the Freest State in the World #4 (1974 final typing) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - In the Freest State in the World #4 (1974 preliminary drafts) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - In the Freest State in the World #4 (notes by Kleins) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Frustration #5 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Burro Trading #6 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Saint in Pain #7, corrections to Michigan Quarterly Review version of The Kidnapped Saint (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Auferweckung des Toten #9 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Indian Dance in the Jungle #10 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Accomplices #11 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Unexpected Solutions #12, rewritten Short Stories version, June 1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Welfare Establishment #13 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Foreign Correspondent (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Dynamite #15 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Primarily second drafts, German versions of Traven stories
    - Der fremde Soldat (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - The Guard, in English translation by Klein (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Mutter Beleke (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Untitled (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Khundar (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Was in Frankreich alles geschehen kann (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Erzählungen (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Rejects: Traven stories in U.S. magazines, 1956-7 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - (Materials for book production)
    - list of materials received from L. Hill, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Critiques from Hill et al. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Table of contents and plans for Hill book (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Im Freiesten Staat der Welt (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Intro I (draft of introduction) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Questions on German translations, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Notes: Diaz regime and Mexico City sanitation (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - 4 stories added in Cassell 1967book, Night Visitor (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - White Rose #1 (excerpt) (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Klein's final drafts for The Kidnapped Saint
    - Submission #2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Diplomats #3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - In the Freest State in the World #4 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Frustration #5 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Burro Trading #6 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - The Kidnapped Saint [draft lacks title page] (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Tin Can #8 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - The Revival of a Dead Man #9 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Indian Dance in the Jungle #10 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Accomplices #11 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Unexpected Solution #12 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - The Welfare Hospital (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Foreign Correspondent #14 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Dynamite #15 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - The Guard #16 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - First 43 galleys, The Kidnapped Saint (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Proofs, The Kidnapped Saint (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Master proofs of The Kidnapped Saint (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Klein's writings and notes on Traven, chronologically ordered
    - Klein drafts of Traven reviews, 1930s (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - New Republic review by Klein, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - New Masses review by Klein, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - British Library: Traven material, 1973,etc. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Büchergilde Gutenberg [Traven publishers], 1926- (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Introduction to The Freest State in the World, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Additional biographical material for Freest State (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Alphabetical guide to Traven material, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Titles for tentative Traven book (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Book on Traven (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Misc. Traven notes, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Klein-Traven letters analyzed (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series III. Subject files
  - Klein's chronological files with notes and/or material on Traven that appeared in each year: periodical articles, BT Mitteilungen, notes from UCLA Special Collections material on Traven. Pre-1920 to 1985,with some omissions
    - Undated file in UCLA Special Collections (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Pre-1920 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1926 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1927 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1928 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1929 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1930 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1931 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 1932 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1933 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1934 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - 1935 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - 1936 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - 1937 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 1938 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - 1939 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - 1940 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - 1942 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - 1943 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - 1944 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - 1945 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - 1946 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - 1947 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - 1948 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - 1949 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - 1950 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - 1951 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - 1952 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - 1953 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - 1954 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - 1955 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - 1956 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - 1957 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1958 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1959 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1960 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1967 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 1970 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - 1971 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - 1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 1973 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - 1974 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - 1975 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - 1976 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - 1977 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - 1978-80 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - 1985 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Bang, Herman, influence on Traven (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Bek-Gray, Robert (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Cheuse, Alan (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Communist press critics of Traven (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Huston, John on Traven (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Land des Frühlings, notes and analysis (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Library of Congress, notes on Traven holdings (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Lopez Mateos, Esperanza (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Manana and Luis Spota (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - The Marut-Traven connection (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Marut (Traven) 1922and earlier (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Powell, L.C. and Traven, Aug. 1976 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Recknagel, Rolf, checklist of articles on Traven (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Revolution, German, notes (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Sex, women, and Traven (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Socialism in Germany, notes (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Spanish language sources on Traven (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Special materials, Universitas-Verlag (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - UCLA Special Collections, MCK file (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Wieder, Josef (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Der Ziegelbrenner, 1917-22,copies and analysis (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Der Ziegelbrenner, notes from British Museum, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Der Ziegelbrenner, notes from Recknagel (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Transcriptions of Marut [Traven] writings by Rolf Recknagel, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Printed materials about Traven, chronologically ordered
    - Articles by Michael Baumann, 1975-77 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Notes from Das B. Traven Buch, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Serial material on Traven, Aug. 1976 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Periodical pieces on BT, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - LA Times, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Reviews of Will Wyatt's book, 1979-80 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Traven material, July 1983 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Traven seminar, USC, Nov. 12, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Materials on Canadian production, 1976-77 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Materials on BBC production, 1977-78 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Films, Traven (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - (Miscellany)
    - Traven mat'l to sort and file (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - German publications of BT books, misc. material (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Newspaper articles about Mexico, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Photos and Audio Tapes
  - Rosa Elena Lujan, Mexico City, Jan. 1973 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Photos from BBC documentary, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Conference photo, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 2 cassettes on P. APC [Philological Association of the Pacific Coast, daughter organization of the MLA] B. Traven Seminar, Los Angeles, Nov. 12, 1977(2.5 hours). Presentations by panelists (Judy Stone, Michael Baumann, Charles Humphrey, Robert Goss, et al.), followed by open discussion moderated by Robert Olafson. The Kleins attended. (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Series V. Books and Play
  - B. Traven, Stories by the Man Nobody Knows (Regency: Evanston, 1961).Annotated paperback. (Box 16, Folder --)
  - Peter Küpfer, Aufklären und Erzählen. Das literarische Frühwerk B. Travens (Diss., Zurich, 1981).[With dedication to Herbert Arthur Klein] (Box 16, Folder --)
  - Robert B. Olafson, The Great Traven Hunt or Erica's Dream. A Play in Three Acts (1977).Copy is lightly annotated. (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Series VI. Serials
  - BT Mitteilungen [subject folder; for location of issues see Addendum] No. 2-11 ed. by Esperanza Lopez Mateos and Josef Wieder (Zurich); no. 12-33 ed. by Josef Wieder (Zurich); no. 24-36 ed. by Rosa Elena Lujan (Mexico City) and Josef Wieder (Zurich). (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - The B. Traven Newsletter. Vol. 1 no. 1 (Autumn-winter 1976)and 2 (summer 1976)ed. by Terrence Ponick, University of South Carolina. [The file includes correspondence with Ponick.] (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Frente a Frente. Organ Central de la Liga de Escritores y Artistas Revolucionarios LEAR Sección Mexicana. Mexico City. Ed. Fernando Gamboa. [Hoover Library has other issues] 1936:3 (Ma). (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Smithsonian. March 1983. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Currents. New York. [SUL has other issues] 1961: Sept. 1975: Oct.(2 copies); Nov.(2 copies); Dec.(2 copies) 1976: Jan.; Feb.; Mar.; Apr.; May; June; July-Aug.; Sept.; Oct.; Nov.; Dec. 1977: Feb. (Box 17, Folder --)
- Series VII. Addendum
  - Serials dispersed throughout the collection:
    - - BT Mitteilungen [subject folder in box 17; SUL has other issues]
      - 1951: 2 (F,missing p. 1-5); 3 (Ap); 4 (Jun); 5 (Au)
      - 1952: 6 (Mar); 7 (May); 8 (Jul); 9 (Oct)
      - 1953: 10 (May); 11 (Aug); 12 (Dec)[incomplete]
      - 1954: 13 (F); 14 (Ap); 15 (Jul); 16 (S); 17 (D)
      - 1955: 18 (Au); 19 (D)[incomplete]
      - 1956: 20 (F); 21 (Jun); 22 (Au); 23 (N)
      - 1957: 24 (Ja); 25 (Ap); 26 (Jul); 27 (Au); 28 (Au)
      - 1958: 29 (Ma); 30 (Au); 31 (Nov); 32 (D)
      - 1959: 33 (Mar); 34 (May); 35 (N)
      - 1960: 36 (Ap) (Box [boxes 10-11])
    - - Der Ziegelbrenner, 1917-22.[SUL has other issues] (Box [box 12])
    - - Büchergilde. Monatsschrift der Büchergilde Gutenberg. Zurich. (Box [boxes 10-11])
      - 1929: 10 (Oct)
      - 1934: 5 (May)
      - 1936: 1 (Ja); 4 (Ap)
      - 1939: 6 (Jun); 9 (Se) 11 (N)
      - 1940: 1 (Ja)
      - 1959: 5 (May); 6 (Jun); 7 (Jul)
    - - Der Bücherfreund. Mitteilungsblatt des Vereins Schweizer Bücherfreunde. Zurich.
      - 1939: 14 (Se); 15 (Oc); 16 (N) (Box [box 10])